we came here looking for a fight mr.
Poirot made a response video - to
something you said in the Joe Rogan
experience do you have anything to say
Oh glad you're asking that I was hoping
it would come up so I don't know how
many people have seen the video and what
it's responding to but the short version
is that I said something on the Joe
Rogan podcast about there being
different kinds of truth that I argued
for something I call metaphorical truth
that something can be literally false
but it can contain wisdom and the way
you know is that if you act as if it
were true you come out ahead of where
you would if you act according to the
fact that it's false and I then said
that scientific truth is the top truth
in the hierarchy and the response was
that it was arrogant of me to say that
there was a top truth that you know
effectively from what position do I do
that and yeah
I can you want to go ahead I just want
to say that's not the argument the
argument is that there was a
performative contradiction in your in
your statement because you talked you
said that factual truth is higher than
metaphorical truth but then to say that
there's a top level truth or that
there's an overarching truth is to use a
metaphorical structure to to demonstrate
where you're placing your truth and so
within the statement there was a car
there as a performative contradiction in
terms of you have to resort to
metaphorical truth to speak of hierarchy
because all the language of hierarchy is
metaphorical and therefore to place
factual truth at the top of that
hierarchy is a performative
contradiction so that's my argument so I
will I will plead guilty to using
metaphor to defend my position because
of course language is composed of
metaphors both living and dead and it's
really hard to communicate anything
without running afoul of that standard
but I will defend in spite of that guilt
I will defend the idea that scientific
truth is the top truth in the hierarchy
and the reason is really simple it's
because there is no mechanism for
sorting between metaphorical truths that
belong to
from traditions and are in conflict with
each other so in other words if we take
to like behave well when you die you go
to heaven that's cool you should do that
on the other hand if you behave well in
Brahman Atman system you may be
reincarnated as something better than
you are now that's also cool but it's
not the same truth right so you can't
sort out these are both kinds of wisdom
and I think we know exactly what kind of
wisdom they are or at least we should
which is if you behave so as to be
reincarnated as something better or to
go to heaven what it will do is in all
probability it will leave your
descendants really well positioned in
their in their culture and that means
that your genes which you might not have
been in a position to say anything about
will be well positioned to persist and
spread because your descendants will be
well placed so in effect going to heaven
or being reincarnated as something
better than you were our stand-ins for a
genetic truth that we can't say and so
what I'm arguing is that what makes the
scientific truth hierarchically superior
is that it explains all the subordinate
truths in a way that is logically
consistent whereas if you were to
prioritize heaven as a truth then you
would have to say well reincarnation is
therefore false or you would have to
have them all simultaneously be true in
some on reconcilable way so the only one
that has the special characteristic of
accounting for all the others is the
scientific truth okay so I think that
what you just did was nested your claim
for the validity of scientific truth
within a pragmatic framework which is
what I claimed when I was talking to Sam
Harris was necessary because you said I
believe that the justification for for
assuming the truth of the of the of the
mythological representation was its
effect on on something that's associated
with a Darwinian process right and
that's how you used that what you used
to justify your claim that it was in
fact true
so in the discussion that you're
referencing my point
so my point was essentially that there
is something called metaphorical truth
and that it's a real thing so I was I'm
in agreement with you on that where we
might be in disagreement is that there
is simultaneously a thing that I would
call literal truth or scientific truth
and by the way I'm not saying that what
scientists say is in this category
inherently scientists can be wrong but
the point is truth that is
scientifically verifiable that makes
predictions has a special priority in
this hierarchy because it is the one
objective version it is not contingent
on being nested in another in a series
of beliefs so what if it's a scientific
truth that's metaphorically wrong oh and
they're like I can give you an example
okay so I read this the memoirs of a KGB
scientist KGB agent who worked with the
Russians in this biochemical lab and
their job was to meld Ebola with
smallpox because smallpox is Ebola is
not that contagious and so that's kind
of annoying if you're trying to kill
people whereas smallpox but it's really
fatal
whereas smallpox is really contagious so
if you could get the two together and
then develop an aerosol spray you could
kill a lot of people and in fact they
did kill about 500 Russians by mistake
when some of what they were doing
escaped but it isn't obvious to me that
that's an invalid scientific pursuit but
I do think that it's an invalid ethical
pursuit and so that seems to me to
indicate that the ethical pursuit
supersedes the scientific pursuit with
regards to truth claim so I'm gonna
disagree with you I would say it doesn't
supersede with respect to the truth
claim it supersedes with respect to
considerations of behavior and policy so
I absolutely agree with you there are
plenty of scientific truths that are
deeply unfortunate and I want to take
what you said the first thing that you
said okay
if you are good you die and you go to
heaven if you're good you die and you're
reincarnated as a higher being those two
things are the same okay in terms of
their effect
there are restating of the hierarchy the
hierarchy religion is all about the
hierarchy that's what religion is about
the the restating of the hierarchy in
those two terms have the same effect in
terms of what we're saying is that if
you're good you will not meld those two
things together and that is the
hierarchy the hierarchy itself is the
capacity to be above quantitative purely
quantitative considerations and to apply
qualitative thinking and the whole
language of hierarchy is all a language
about a movement from from quantity up
to quality like that it's it's movement
it's about going up a mountain it's
going up the base and then going up to
you to unity and when you stand in that
top place then you can look down and you
can judge what facts because there are
there is an innumerable amounts of fact
there's an infinite quantity of facts
you can decide which facts are worth
pursuing and so that's what religion is
and that's what the hierarchy is so if
you take if you take qualitative if you
take a quantitative tidbit of
information and you say that is above
let's say qualitative judgment how do
you even why why are you even focusing
on that quantitative data because
there's there's an infinite amount of
them so you have to have a Matt a manner
by which you focus on something and that
is the hierarchy and that is the whole
language of of the religious hierarchy
so so what do you do where religious
traditions and what I'm calling
metaphorical truths conflict so let's
say mating systems I would argue that
monogamy is a
superior mating system because it does
not sideline any significant population
of males
if you sideline a significant population
of males by having what biologists would
call a polygynous system or people would
generally call a polygamous system if
you do that then you have sexually
frustrated males who are left over and
inevitably become something like a
marauding horde or an army or something
immoral like that now wait wait
now you're assuming that's bad yeah and
so you're falling into Jonathan's trap
because you're saying you see you have
this a priori framework that monogamy is
better because you've already decided
what constitutes bad you can't help but
lay a moral framework over your
selection of facts and so that I mean
I'm not trying to trap you I know this
is a crazily complicated problem yeah
but but the idea that you that that the
fundamental idea is that you can't
select the damn facts and order them
which you have to do you have to do it
without applying an a priori moral
framework right so I would say I am
applying an a priori moral framework I
am NOT treating this as us I mean you
know we could also look at the behavior
of people as a physical process it's
equally a physical process as it is a
moral behavioral process I'm not doing
that I'm being a human being and I'm
saying from the point of view of values
that probably everybody in this room
would share it is not desirable to have
sexually frustrated young men roving
around being violent because they can't
find a mate because some other
highly-placed males in the society have
many mates that's not a good thing
that's not me speaking factually that's
me speaking morally but my point my
point is not that that's what should
come out of this conversation my point
is different religions that contain
metaphorical truths differ over what a
viable reproductive strategy is in other
words Christianity prioritizes monogamy
modern Judaism does too but the Torah
does not so okay so so okay so your
claim is that because it's very
difficult to adjudicate between
competing moral systems that science is
prayer
furball with regards to truth claims
because there's a way of adjudicating
between scientific truths but I would
say the mere fact that it's difficult to
adjudicate between competing moral
claims doesn't indicate therefore that
science is a higher truth it just
indicates that science has an advantage
when it comes to comparison that ethical
systems don't it doesn't means that
ethical systems are perfect no no I so
this is one of these places where I
don't exactly know what I'm running
afoul of and why I think my brain is
built around some sort of model that
makes it hard for me to understand why
we could possibly be disagreeing over
this my point is you have a thousand
different belief systems they're all
built out of metaphorical truths in a
certain amount of real truth let's just
stick science in with the rest of them
its its belief system a thousand and one
okay now let's say well which of these
is best how are you even going to do
that there's only one of them that has a
distinct characteristic its number a
thousand and one what's its distinct
characteristic it explains why all the
others work so how is it not just by
virtue of the fact that it does
something that nothing else can
how is it not the top one in the
hierarchy we have run a little bit past
eight would we would you all want to
would all be interested in getting
together for a an organized debate like
a little tag team Peterson patch out
versus Weinstein Harris sure okay well
that's a good place to end so
[Music]
um that's it so we have the reception
I'll explain the yeah I'll explain the
stuff about the reception now it's at
11:28 west hastings
you go up Erard until you get to west
hastings you take a ripe and it's like
two blocks up on your left it's a
five-minute walk
got room for like a hundred people so
you know first-come first-serve I
suppose free food not free drinks but
I'll be worth it and yeah that's it so
thank you all very very very much for
coming we really appreciate it and have
a good night